Guide to the New Almaden Mine (Calif.) Collection, 1845-1973
Department of Special Collections
- SERIES VII: MAPS AND PLANS
  - ROLLED MAPS
    - Pueblo lands, tract #3, Rancho de los Capitancillos, Rancho San Vicente, boundary coordinates, blueprint, old #254, 1926; 57x 10ch (Folder 120)
      California Pacific Titl and Trust
    - Composite map of Harry workings, 1944; 37x43 50 (Folder 121)
    - Preliminary Survey for pipe line from spring to supply Garfield shaft old #300, 1882; 28x47 200 (Folder 122)
    - Santa Rita, Junction shaft, 38x42 (Folder 123)
    - Santa Rita, Junction shaft, 38x42 (Folder 124)
    - Profile showing the Hacienda tunnel and Grey and Cora Blanca shafts, 1876; 24x106 40 (Folder 125)
    - Contours, Don Ricardo, Paull tunnel, Lower Grover tunnel, Little Grover tunnel, 58x (Folder 126)
    - Topographical map of the property of the Quicksilver Mining Company, 1887; 60x184 200 (Folder 127)
      Sidney Jennin
    - Plan of the Senator mine, 1919; 58x87 50 (Folder 128)
      C.W. Ferry
    - Tunnel plans, Randol shaft, 56x84 (Folder 129)
    - San Mateo, San Antonio, 54x57 (Folder 130)
    - Working map, deep levels of the New Almaden Mine, 1878; 60x93 20 (Folder 131)
      Ross E. Brown
    - Map of the New Almaden and other mines on the property of the Quicksilver Mining Company, 52·169 60 (Folder 132)
    - Topographical map, 61x103 (Folder 133)
    - Work done since 1883, major tunnels, signed by Charles Derby and three others, 1885 (Folder 134)
  - GLASS DIORAMA
    - 3 panes, stored between plastic, 2 broken, 8.5x27
    - 3 panes, stored between plastic, 2 broken, 8.5x11
    - 2 panes, stored between plastic, 8.5x11
    - Wooden stand, with mylar covered map, 25x30x3.75
- SERIES VIII: RESEARCH NOTES
  - NOTES
    - McMurry, George, correspondence, 1933-1954 (Box 105, Folder 1)
    - McMurry, George, with Bulmore, 1939-1942 (Box 105, Folder 2)
    - McMurry, documents, transcriptions, 1776-1863 (Box 105, Folder 3)
    - McMurry, documents, transcriptions, 1864-1882 (Box 105, Folder 4)
    - McMurry, documents, transcriptions, 1888-1937 (Box 105, Folder 5)
    - McMurry, letters of the Quicksilver Mining Company, transcriptions, 1859-1866 (Box 105, Folder 6)
    - McMurry, letters of the Quicksilver Mining Company, transcriptions, 1864-1895 (Box 106, Folder 1)
    - McMurry, letters of the Quicksilver Mining Company, transcriptions, 1910-1915 (Box 106, Folder 2)
    - McMurry, letters of the Quicksilver Mining Company, transcriptions, 1915-1927 (Box 106, Folder 3)
    - McMurry, newsclippings (Box 106, Folder 4)
    - McMurry, note cards, accidents-characters (Box 107)
    - McMurry, note cards, chronology-interviews
    - McMurry, note cards, Knox and Osbourne-political (Box 108)
    - McMurry, note cards, priviledges-selling
    - McMurry, note cards, seniority-weather, general mine data-march tunnel (Box 109)
    - McMurry, note cards, Mine Hill-Santa Maria (Box 110)
    - McMurry, note cards, Santa Mariana-Yellow Kid Jr.
    - McMurry, notes, n.d. (Box 111, Folder 1)
    - McMurry, notes, n.d. (Box 111, Folder 2)
    - McMurry, notes, n.d. (Box 111, Folder 3)
    - McMurry, photographs, (64) (Box 111, Folder 4)
    - McMurry, photograph identifications (Box 111, Folder 5)
    - McMurry, primary resources (Box 111, Folder 6)
    - Research notes, unidentified (Box 111, Folder 7)
    - Schneider, Jimmie, correspondence, 1940, 1968 (Box 111, Folder 8)
    - Schneider, Jimmie, with William Bishop, 1955-1963 (Box 111, Folder 9)
    - Schneider, Jimmie, with Francis Frederick, 1962-1967 (Box 111, Folder 10)
    - Schneider, map of New Almaden, 1952 (Box 111, Folder 11)
    - Schneider, notes (Box 111, Folder 12)
- SERIES IX: PUBLICATIONS & PRINTED MATERIAL 1843-1977
  - MONOGRAPHS AND PUBLISHED MATERIALS, 1859-1977
    - A. Lietz Company. Surveying and Drafting Supplies: General Catalog. San Francisco: [1938]., 436 pp. (Volume 65)
    - Appeal and Petitions for Voluntary Dissolution of Quicksilver Mining Company. [Aug. 1918]., 507 pp. (Box 112, Folder 1)
    - Armstrong, R., C.E. Chimneys for Furnaces, Fireplaces, and Steam Boilers. New York: D. Van Nostrand, 1873., 76 pp. (Box 111, Folder 2)
    - Asher, Leonardo, The New Almaden Mine, 1845-1863, Thesis (Box 111, Folder 3)
    - Atkinson, J.J. A Practical Treatise on Friction of Air in Mines. New York: D. Van Nostrand, 1875., 69 pp. (Box 111, Folder 4)
    - Babson's Reports: Buyer's Bulletin. Massachusetts: Oct. 2, 1923., 6 pp. (Box 111, Folder 5)
    - Bailey, Edgar H., The New Almaden Quicksilver Mines printed in Geological Guidebook of the San Francisco Bay Counties # 154, San Francisco, 1951 (Box 111, Folder 6)
    - Bailey, Edgar and Everhart, Donald, Geology and Quicksilver Deposits of the New Almaden District, Santa Clara County, California, Geological Survey Professional Paper #360, Washington, D.C., 1964, 206 pp. (Volume 66)
    - Becker, George F. Quicksilver Ore Deposits, (Dept. of the Interior: U.S. Geological Survey). Washington: Government Printing Office, 1893., 39 pp. (Box 111, Folder 7)
    - Bedford, Robert H., Spangler, Ricker, Investigation of the New Almaden Mercury Mine, Santa Clara County, California, Department of the Interior, Washington, D.C., 1950 (Box 111, Folder 8)
    - Bernaldez, Dn. Fernando, Figueroa, Dn. Ramon Rua, Memoris of the mines of Almaden and Almadenjos, 1861 (Volume 67)
    - California Quicksilver, (Reprinted from the Evening Bulletin). May, 1884., 18 pp. (Box 111, Folder 9)
    - California Quicksilver. San Francisco: 1890., 13 pp. (Box 111, Folder 10)
    - California State Mining Bureau- Fletcher Hamilton, State Mineralogist. Quicksilver Resources of California: Bulletin #78. Sacramento: California State Printing Office, 1918., 389 pp. (Volume 68)
    - The California State Mining Bureau- Lewis Aubury, State Mineralogist. The Quicksilver Resources of California. Sacramento: W.W. Shannon, 1980., 273 pp. (Volume 69)
    - Christy, Samuel B. Quicksilver-Condensation at New Almaden, California. Philadelphia: Sherman & Co., Printers, 1885., 60 pp. (Box 111, Folder 11)
    - Christy, Samuel B. Quicksilver-Reduction at New Almaden, (photocopy)., 38 pp. (Box 111, Folder 12)
    - Christy, Samuel B. (translator and compiler), Vermillion, Its Properties and Manufacture, handwritten, 1879, 170 pp. (Volume 70)
    - A Contested Election in California, (Sullivan vs. Felton). Reprinted from San Jose Daily Mercury, Santa Clara Co., Calif., 1887., 163 pp. (Box 111, Folder 13)
    - A Contested Election, (Sullivan vs. Hon. C.N. Felton). Reprinted from San Jose Daily Mercury, Santa Clara Co., Calif., 1887., 144 pp.
    - A Contested Election in California, (Testimony of New Almaden). Reprinted from San Jose Daily Mercury, Santa Clara Co., Calif. 1887., 160 pp. (Box 113, Folder 1)
    - Dietzgen Catalog No. 94E: Surveying Equipment. Chicago: Eugene Dietzgen Co., 1939., 128 pp. (Box 113, Folder 2)
    - Dixon, Thomas. The Practical Millwright's & Engineer's Ready Reckoner. London: E & F. N. Spon, 1878., 93 pp. (Volume 71)
    - Dobson, Edward. Foundations and Concrete Works. London: Crosby, Lockwood & Co., 1881., 120 pp. (Volume 72)
    - Dobson, Edward. The Rudiments of Masonry and Stonecutting. London: Crosby, Lockwood & Co., 1878., 146 pp. & 12 plates. (Volume 73)
    - Down in the Cinnabar Mines, Harper's Monthly Magazine #CLXXXV, October 1865., 14 pp. (Box 113, Folder 3)
    - Engineering & Mining Journal. E & MJ Metal and Mineral Markets. New York: McGraw-Hill Publishing Co.; Aug.1942-Oct.1943, Jan.1944-Sept.1945, Sept. 1945-Apr.1946. (Box 113, Folder 4-6)
    - Haesemeyer, Joni, The Founding and Settlement of New Almaden (Box 113, Folder 7)
    - Haupt, Lewis M. A Manual of Engineering Specifications and Contracts. Philadelphia: J.M. Stoddart & Co., 1878., 305 pp. (Volume 74)
    - IBM, Santa Teresa Laboratory: A Place in History (Box 113, Folder 8)
    - Illinois Electric Co. General Catalogue No. 11. Chicago., 462 pp. (Volume 75)
    - Innes, A.C., New Almaden (New Almaden Fifty Years Ago) (Box 113, Folder 9)
    - Keuffel & Esser Co. Catalogue of Keuffel & Esser Co.: Drawing Materials, Surveying Instruments, Measuring Tapes. New York: 1936., 581 pp. (Volume 76)
    - Lanyon, Milton & Laurence Bulmore. Clinnabar Hills: The Quicksilver Days of New Almaden, (photocopy). Los Gatos, Calif.: Village Printers, 1968., 127 pp. (Box 114, Folder 1)
    - McCaskey, H.D. Production of Quicksilver in 1909, (Dept. of the Interior: U.S. Geological Survey). Washington: Government Printing Office, 1911., 13 pp. (Box 114, Folder 2)
    - McCaskey, H.D. Production of Quicksilver in 1910, (Dept. of the Interior: U.S. Geological Survey). Washington: Government Printing Office, 1911., 20 pp.
    - McCaskey, H.D. Quicksilver in 1911: Production and Resources, (Dept. of the Interior: U.S. Geological Survey). Washington: Government Printing Office, 1912., 35 pp.
    - McMurry, George, typescripts (Box 114, Folder 3)
    - McMurry, Reminiscences of the Almaden Mines, by Judge A.C. Innes (Box 114, Folder 4)
    - The Miner's Association of Cornwall and Devon, (Reports and Proceedings for 1873). Falmouth: Lake & Co., 1874., 98 pp. (Box 114, Folder 5)
    - Mining Accident at New Almaden, California. San Francisco. 1888., 15 pp. (Box 114, Folder 6)
    - Morgans, William. Atlas of Engravings to Illustrate the Manual of Mining Tools. London: Lockwood & Co., 1871., 20 plates. (Volume 77)
    - Overman, Fred. Mechanics for the Millwright, Machinist, Engineer.... Philadelphia: J.B. Lippincott & Co., 1864., 420 pp. (Volume 78)
    - Quicksilver Mines of Almaden & New Almaden: A Comparative View of their Extent, Production, Costs of Work, Etc. Printed for private circulation, 1886., 15 pp. (Box 114, Folder 7)
    - The Quicksilver Mines at New Almaden, Harper's Monthly Magazine #CLVII, June 1863., 17pp. (Box 114, Folder 8)
      and Down in The Cinnabar Mines, in Harpers, on 1865, # CLXXXV, v. XXXI, pp 545-560.
    - Rand Drill Co. Illustrated Catalogue of Rand Drill Co. New York., 128 pp. (Box 114, Folder 9)
    - Randol, J.B. Quicksilver and the Tariff in the House of Representatives and Elsewhere. San Francisco: 1890., 20 pp. (Box 114, Folder 10)
    - Reed, Lieutenant Henry A. Photography Applied to Surveying. New York: John Wiley & Sons, 1888., 68 pp. (Volume 79)
    - Report of the State Mineralogist. [San Francisco]: 1888., 948 pp. (Volume 80)
    - Reprints, unidentified (Box 114, Folder 11)
    - Schmidt, W.A. Dust and Fume Collection by Cottrell Processes of Electrical Precipitation. Los Angeles: 1916., 48 pp. (Box 114, Folder 12)
    - Schneider, Jimmie, Typescript, More Music than Gold: The Story of the New Almaden Mine, part 1 (Box 114, Folder 13)
    - Schneider, Jimmie, Typescript, More Music than Gold: The Story of the New Almaden Mine, part 2 (Box 114, Folder 14)
    - Schneider, Jimmie, Typescript, More Music than Gold: The Story of the New Almaden Mine, part 3 (Box 115, Folder 1)
    - Shutes, Milton H. Abraham Lincoln and the New Almaden Mine, (Reprinted from Calif. Historical Society Quarterly). San Francisco: Lawton R. Kennedy, March 1936., 20 pp. (Box 115, Folder 2)
    - Slater, Dudley, Land Claim Disputes at New Almaden (Box 115, Folder 3)
    - Transactions of the American Institute of Mining Engineers Feb. 1888, Sept.-Oct. 1890., (19 articles). (Box 115, Folder 4)
    - United States Centennial Commission. International Exhibition, 1876: AWARDS. Philadelphia: J.B. Lippincott & Co., 1878., 39 pp. (Box 115, Folder 5)
    - United States Centennial Commission. International Exhibition, 1876: REPORTS & AWARDS. Philadelphia: J.B. Lippincott & Co., 1877-78.Group I (Box 115, Folder 6)
    - United States Centennial Commission. International Exhibition, 1876: REPORTS & AWARDS. Philadelphia: J.B. Lippincott & Co., 1877-78.,Group IV (Box 115, Folder 7)
    - United States Centennial Commission. International Exhibition, 1876: REPORTS & AWARDS. Philadelphia: J.B. Lippincott & Co., 1877-78.,Groups V-VIII, XIII (Box 115, Folder 8)
    - United States Centennial Commission. International Exhibition, 1876: REPORTS & AWARDS. Philadelphia: J.B. Lippincott & Co., 1877-78.,Groups XV, XVI, XVIII, XXI, XXIV-XXVII (Box 116, Folder 1)
    - United States Centennial Commission. International Exhibition, 1876: REPORTS & AWARDS. Philadelphia: J.B. Lippincott & Co., 1877-78.,Groups XXVIII-XXXVI (Box 116, Folder 2)
    - Up and Down California (Box 116, Folder 3)
    - Valencia, Francisco, New Almaden and the Mexican, Thesis, 1977 (Box 116, Folder 4)
    - Van Nostrand's Monthly Record of Scientific Literature, Nos. 1-24: May 15, 1872-Apr. 15, 1874. New York: D. Van Nostrand, 1874., 207 pp. (Volume 81)
    - Wells, A.E. The Wet Thiogen Process for Recovering Sulphur from Sulphur Dioxide in Smelter Gases, (Dept. of the Interior: Bulletin 133). Washington: Government Printing Office, 1917., 66 pp. (Box 116, Folder 5)
  - NEWSCLIPPINGS 1843-1970 & n.d.
    - Newspaper Clippings, n.d. (Box 116, Folder 6)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1 Apr. 1843 (Box 7)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1855-60 (Box 116, Folder 7)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1905-29 (Box 116, Folder 8)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1931-39 (Box 116, Folder 9)
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1940-70 (Box 116, Folder 10)
  - PRINTED FLYERS 1876-1953 & n.d.
    - Printed Flyers, 1876-1953 (Box 116, Folder 11)
    - Printed Flyers, n.d. (Box 116, Folder 12)
      (arranged alphabetically)
- SERIES X: PHOTOGRAPHS
  - PRINTS
    - Alamitos Creek, (1) (Box 117, Folder 1)
    - Band, Almaden, (4) (Box 117, Folder 2)
    - Baseball, Almaden teams, (5) (Box 117, Folder 3)
    - Boarding House, Hacienda, (4) (Box 117, Folder 4)
    - Boarding House, Hill (Englishtown), (5) (Box 117, Folder 5)
    - Boarding House, Interior (no identification), (2) (Box 117, Folder 6)
    - Boarding House, The Five Nations' House, Spanishtown, (1) (Box 117, Folder 7)
    - Bridges, Hacienda, (11) (Box 117, Folder 8)
    - Buildings, unidentified, (40) (Box 117, Folder 9)
    - Bulmores, The, (5) (Box 117, Folder 10)
    - Butterworth, Samuel Fowler, (1) (Box 117, Folder 11)
    - Casa Grande, Chinese Pagoda, (14) (Box 117, Folder 12)
    - Casa Grande, Grounds, (2) (Box 117, Folder 13)
    - Casa Grande, House, (7) (Box 117, Folder 14)
    - Casa Grande, Lagoon, (7) (Box 117, Folder 15)
    - Cemetery Hill, (1) (Box 117, Folder 16)
    - Cemetary, Mexican, (1) (Box 117, Folder 17)
    - Centennial of George Washington's Inaguration, miner with banner at New Almaden, (2) (Box 117, Folder 18)
    - Cinnabar, The New Almaden Mine's Rose Carnival Float, (5) (Box 117, Folder 19)
    - Church, Englishtown, last M.E. church, (2) (Box 117, Folder 20)
    - Church, Spanishtown, last catholic church, (2) (Box 117, Folder 21)
    - Church, unidentified, (4) (Box 117, Folder 22)
    - Cinco de Mayo, Spanishtown, (2) (Box 117, Folder 23)
    - Colgante de Judas Iscariot, Good Friday celebration, Spanishtown, (8) (Box 117, Folder 24)
    - Cora Blanca, (2) (Box 117, Folder 25)
    - Derby, Thomas, (1) (Box 117, Folder 26)
    - Dam, Almaden, (2) (Box 117, Folder 27)
    - Englishtown, (59 plus 7 paper tracings) (Box 117, Folder 28)
    - Firehouse, (1) (Box 118, Folder 1)
    - Firehouse #1, (1) (Box 12)
    - Fourth of July Celebrations, (3) (Box 118, Folder 2)
    - Gabble Town, (3) (Box 118, Folder 3)
    - Guadalupe Mine, Buildings and Surrounding Area, (21) (Box 118, Folder 4)
    - Guadalupe Mine, Machinery, (4) (Box 118, Folder 5)
    - Hacienda, Acequia, (13) (Box 118, Folder 6)
    - Hacienda, buildings, furnaces, mine, (11) (Box 12)
    - Hacienda, Furnace Yard and Surrounding Work Areas, (56) (Box 118, Folder 7)
    - Hacienda, Homes, (7) (Box 118, Folder 8)
    - Hacienda, Store, (7) (Box 118, Folder 9)
    - Harry, Captain, Cottage, (2) (Box 118, Folder 10)
    - Helping Hand Club, Hacienda and Hill, (6) (Box 118, Folder 11)
    - Hill Office, (11) (Box 118, Folder 12)
    - Hunting, (5) (Box 118, Folder 13)
    - Incline Railroad, (14) (Box 118, Folder 14)
    - Knights of Pythias, (5) (Box 118, Folder 15)
    - Lower shed, Almaden Mines, (1) (Box 118, Folder 16)
    - Machinery, mines, unidentified, (36) (Box 118, Folder 17)
    - Maps, photographs of, (78) (Box 118, Folder 18)
    - Mine Hill, (1) (Box 119, Folder 1)
    - Miscellaneous, illustrations from articles, (24) (Box 119, Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous, landscapes, aerial, unidentified, (24) (Box 119, Folder 3)
    - Nature shots, (16) (Box 119, Folder 4)
    - New Idria Mine, (1) (Box 119, Folder 5)
    - (Orchestra, (3) (Box 119, Folder 6)
    - People, Miners, identified, (9) (Box 119, Folder 7)
    - People, Miners, unidentified, (27) (Box 119, Folder 8)
    - People, non-mine workers, identified, (19) (Box 119, Folder 9)
    - People, non-mine workers, unidentified, (32) (Box 119, Folder 10)
    - People, officials, group shots, (4) (Box 119, Folder 11)
    - Picnics, (5) (Box 119, Folder 12)
    - Pioche Vichy Springs, (1) (Box 119, Folder 13)
    - Play casts, (4) (Box 119, Folder 14)
    - Randol, James Butterworth, (1) (Box 119, Folder 15)
    - Randol Planilla, (8) (Box 119, Folder 16)
    - Randol Planilla, (1) (Box 12)
    - Rifle Club, (4) (Box 119, Folder 17)
    - School, Guadalupe, (1) (Box 119, Folder 18)
    - School, Hacienda, (8) (Box 120, Folder 1)
    - School, Hill, (Englishtown) (14) (Box 120, Folder 2)
    - School, Mexican (Spanishtown), (2) (Box 120, Folder 3)
    - Senator Furnace Construction, (34) (Box 120, Folder 4)
    - Shaft, Almaden, (2) (Box 120, Folder 5)
    - Shaft, America, (2) (Box 120, Folder 6)
    - Shaft, Buena Vista, (12) (Box 120, Folder 7)
    - Shaft, Harry, (6) (Box 120, Folder 8)
    - Shaft, Randol, (16) (Box 120, Folder 9)
    - Shaft, Randol, (6) (Box 12)
    - Shaft, St. George, (4) (Box 120, Folder 10)
    - Shaft, Santa Isabel, (9) (Box 120, Folder 11)
    - Shaft, Santa Isabel, (2) (Box 12)
    - Shaft, Victoria, (2) (Box 120, Folder 12)
    - Shaft, Washington, (6) (Box 120, Folder 13)
    - Spanishtown, (47) (Box 120, Folder 14)
    - Spanishtown, (6) (Box 12)
    - Stage, Almaden, (10) (Box 120, Folder 15)
    - Ten Mile House, Los Gatos, (1) (Box 120, Folder 16)
    - Top of Mine, (1) (Box 120, Folder 17)
    - Unidentified (Box 120, Folder 18)
    - Unidentified, Behrman prints, (2) (Box 120, Folder 19)
    - Unidentified, (2) (Box 12)
    - Varcoe, Captain, House, (1) (Box 120, Folder 20)
    - Whims, (4) (Box 120, Folder 21)
    - Yellow Kid Open Cut, (6) (Box 120, Folder 22)
  - NOTES
    - Photograph identifications (Box 120, Folder 23)
  - NEGATIVES
    - FILM BASE
      - Buildings, unidentified Behrman 1, 4, 7, 11, (4) (Othertype Nit. Shelv.)
      - Cemetary, Item 1 (Box 120, Folder 24)
      - Cemetary, headstone, Item 2
      - Document, signed by Juan Varga, Item 3
      - Englishtown, Item 4 (Box 120, Folder 24)
      - Englishtown, (2) Watkins stereograph copy negative, Behrman 6, 5 (Othertype Nit. Shelv.)
      - Harry, Captain James, cottage, Item 5 (Box 120, Folder 24)
      - Knights of Pythias, Item 6
      - Knights of Pythias, #2 (Othertype Nit. Shelv.)
      - Knights of Pythias, #2, identifications, Item 7 (Box 120, Folder 24)
      - Machinery, Day Tunnel compressor, early 1900s,Item 8
      - Mexican camp, Item 9
      - Mine workers (Othertype Nit. Shelv.)
      - New Almaden, (2), Item 10 (Box 120, Folder 24)
      - New Almaden, Behrman 2, 3, 9, 10, (4) (Othertype Nit. Shelv.)
      - Unsorted 35mm negatives; singly, in strips, and in rolls. With contact prints matched to some (Box 121)
    - GLASS NEGATIVES
      - 46 whole glass plate negatives, 11 broken (Box 13-16)